<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-haas-savnet-bgp-sav-distribution-00"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP SAV Distribution">Distribution of Source Address Validation State in BGP</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-haas-savnet-bgp-sav-distribution-00"/>
   
    <author fullname="Jeffrey Haas" initials="J." surname="Haas">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>US</country>
          </postal>
          <email>jhaas@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date year="2024"/>

    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>BGP</keyword>
    <keyword>SAV</keyword>
    <keyword>source address validation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Source Address Validation (SAV) is a technique that can be used to
        mitigate source address spoofing.  draft-huang-savnet-sav-table codifies
        the concept of source address validation on a per-incoming interface
        basis, the validation mode, and the traffic handling policy as a 
        "SAV Table".
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines a mechanism for distributing logical SAV Tables in
        BGP.  This mechanism is addresses inter-domain SAV use cases.  These SAV
        Tables may be used to implement appropriate device-specific validation
        for source addresses.
      </t>
    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Introductory text</t>
      
      <section anchor="requirements">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>
        The following terminology is defined in
        <xref target="I-D.huang-savnet-sav-table"/>:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>SAV rule:</dt>
        <dd>The entry specifying the valid incoming interfaces of specific
          source addresses or source prefixes.</dd>

        <dt>Traffic handling policy:</dt>
        <dd>The policy taken on the packets validated by SAV.</dd>

        <dt>Validation mode:</dt>
        <dd>The mode that describes the typical applications of SAV in a specific
          kind of scenarios. Different modes take effect in different scales and
          treat the default prefix differently.</dd>
      </dl>

      <t>
        The following terminology is defined in this document:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>BGP SAV-dist Entry (SAV-D Entry):</dt>
        <dd>A tuple consisting of a source address prefix, validation mode, and
          traffic handling policy.</dd>

        <dt>BGP SAV-dist Target (SAV-D Target):</dt>
        <dd>An attribute declaring membership of a BGP SAV-dist Entry in one or
          more BGP SAV-dist Tables.</dd>

        <dt>BGP SAV-dist Table (SAV-D Table):</dt>
        <dd>A logical table defined by a set of BGP SAV-dist Targets and the BGP
          SAV-dist Entries matching those targets.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <name>A model for SAV distribution</name>

      <t>
        Source address validation can be modeled on a per-interface basis as a
        match operation on a list of prefixes.  Upon a match, or failure to
        match, a traffic handling policy is applied to the traffic.  An instance
        of a prefix, its validation mode, and its traffic handling policy is a
        SAV rule.
      </t>
      <t>
        In the inter-domain SAV use case, this set of prefixes consists of the
        set of upstream networks that may receive the advertised BGP routes,
        either directly or transitively, where the forwarding element is a BGP
        next hop.  Determining this set of upstream prefixes is the subject of a
        number of savnet proposals.
      </t>
      <t>
        A given SAV rule may be applied to a number of forwarding elements
        on the same device, or across multiple devices.
      </t>
      <t>
        It can be observed that a given SAV rule that might be applied to a
        given interface by a provisioning mechanism follows several common
        membership criteria:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>This rule is for this specific interface on a device.</li>
        <li>This rule is for a set of interfaces on this device that may share a
          common property.  For example, "all customer interfaces".</li>
        <li>This rule is for a set of interfaces across the network (Autonomous
          System) that may share a common property.  For example, all interfaces
          for a given service provider.</li>
        <li>This rule is for a prefix from an upstream BGP Autonomous
          System.</li>
      </ul>

      <t>A "SAV Table" may be modeled as the interface-specific list of
        memberships for SAV rules that share those membership criteria.</t>

      <t>These properties have some similarity with Layer 3 VPNs.  A SAV entry
        may be modeled as a BGP route that is a member of some number of SAV-D
        Tables via one or more SAV-D Targets.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>SAV-D Routes</name>
      
      <t>
        A SAV-D Route implements an instance of a SAV rule.  As noted above, SAV
        rules consist of a prefix, a validation mode, and a traffic handling
        policy.
      </t>
      <t>
        A prefix for a SAV-D Route may have a large number of memberships across
        a deployment.  Since baseline BGP is limited by its PDU size to 4096
        bytes, the prefix alone cannot be the "NLRI key".  In order to permit a
        large number of memberships for a given prefix, this document defines a
        new Route Distinguisher.  The prefix is encoded in a BGP NLRI with a new
        SAFI, defined below.  The validation mode and traffic handling policies
        are encoded in new BGP Extended Communities <xref target="RFC4360"/>.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>SAV-D RD-Originator</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="RD-Originator">
            <![CDATA[
  Type Field: TBD (2 octets)
  Value Field: 6 octets

 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type: TBD                     |    Global Administrator       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Global Administrator (cont.)  |    Local Administrator        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </artset>      

        <t>
          The Global Administrator field contains the BGP Identifier of the BGP
          speaker originating these SAV-D routes.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Local Administrator contains a locally chosen value that permits
          unique combinations of SAV-D Routes to be distributed across the
          deployment.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>SAV-D NLRI</name>

        <t>
          This document defines two new BGP NLRI types, AFI=1/2, SAFI=TBD, which
          can be used to distribute SAV Rules in BGP.

          The NLRI format for this address family consists of a fixed-length 8
          octet SAV-D RD-Originator followed by a variable-length IPv4 or IPv6
          prefix whose length depends on AFI.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>SAV-D Match Extended Community</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="SAV-D Match Extended Community">
            <![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type      |   Sub-Type     |              0                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     0                         |     Value     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type: TBD
Sub-Type: TBD
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </artset>      
        <t>
          The first five octets of this Extended Community's Value field MUST be
          zero.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Value of this extended community can be:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>1:</dt>
          <dd>Allow.  Traffic matching this source address has passed the
            local validation criteria and will continue to be processed in the
            forwarding pipeline.</dd>
          <dt>2:</dt>
          <dd>Block.  Traffic matching this source address has failed validation
            and will be blocked.</dd>
          <dt>3:</dt>
          <dd>Action. Traffic matching this source address is subject to further
            evaluation based on the SAV-D Route Traffic Handling procedures.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Encoding SAV-D Route Traffic Handling Actions</name>

        <t>
          When traffic has the "Action" match criteria, the traffic is subject
          to additional processing when supported by the local forwarding
          element.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following extended communities are re-used from 
          <xref target="RFC8955" section="7"/>:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>traffic-rate-bytes - rate-limiting bps.</li>
          <li>traffic-rate-packets - rate-limit pps.</li>
          <li>rt-redirect AS-2octet - traffic redirection by VRF.</li>
          <li>rt-redirect AS-4octet - traffic redirection by VRF.</li>
          <li>rt-redirect IPv4 - traffic redirection by VRF.</li>
          <li>traffic-marking - traffic marking DSCP.</li>
          <li>traffic-action, S-bit only - sampling. All other bits MUST be zero.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          The following extended communities are re-used from 
          <xref target="RFC8956" section="7"/>:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>rt-redirect IPv6 - traffic redirection by VRF.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          The following extended communities are re-used from
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"/>:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Flow-spec Redirect to IPv4</li>
          <li>Flow-spec Redirect to IPv6</li>
        </ul>
        <section>
          <name>Error handling for SAV-D Traffic Handling Actions</name>

          <t>
            A BGP speaker might not be able to process some or any of the traffic
            handling actions.  Since SAV tables are intended to be provisioned on
            a per-device per-interface basis, BGP speakers generating SAV-D routes
            should have an understanding of what features can be implemented by
            the receiving device and avoid encoding actions that cannot be
            implemented by that device.
          </t>
          <t>
            The following error handling behaviors are specified for SAV-D
            routes containing actions:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>A SAV-D route MUST NOT contain more than one redirection action.  
              If a BGP speaker receives more than one redirection action it MAY
              locally permit traffic to be allowed or blocked based on
              provisioning.</li>
            <li>A BGP speaker unable to implement redirection MAY locally permit
              traffic to be allowed or blocked based on provisioning.</li>
            <li>A BGP speaker unable to implement rate-limiting MAY locally
              permit traffic to be allowed or blocked based on provisoning.</li>
            <li>A BGP speaker unable to implement traffic-marking MAY locally
              permit traffic to be allowed or blocked based on provisoning.</li>
            <li>A BGP speaker unable to implement sampling SHOULD permit traffic
              to be allowed.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>SAV-D Targets</name>

      <t>SAV-D Routes are members of one or more SAV-D Tables.  This membership
        is signaled in SAV-D Routes using one or more SAV-D Target Extended
        Communities.</t>

      <t>
        Some SAV-D Targets are node-specific.  In order to clearly encode such
        node-specific SAV-D Extended Communities and appropriately scope them,
        routes containing SAV-D node-specific Extended Communities MUST contain a
        single instance of a Node Target Extended Community, 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-node-target-ext-comm"/>.
      </t>

      <section>
        <name>SAV-D Interface Member Extended Community</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="SAV-D Interface Member Extended Community">
            <![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type       |   Sub-Type    |    Global Administrator       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Global Administrator (cont.)  |               0               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type: TBD - non-transitive
Sub-Type: TBD
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </artset>      
        <t>
          This is a SAV-D node-specific Extended Community type and requires a
          Node Target Extended Community for context.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Global Administrator field is set to the ifIndex 
          <xref target="RFC1213"/> of the interface that the SAV Rule is a
          member of.  The Local Administrator field MUST be set to zero.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>SAV-D Device-Specific Group Member Extended Community</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="SAV-D Device-Specific Group Member Extended Community">
            <![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type       |   Sub-Type    |          Value...             ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
~                           ...Value                            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type: TBD - non-transitive
Sub-Type: TBD
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </artset>      
        <t>
          This is a SAV-D node-specific Extended Community type and requires a
          Node Target Extended Community for context.
        </t>
        <t>
          The 6-octet value is has local significance to the node.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>SAV-D Neighbor-AS Member Extended Community</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="SAV-D Neighbor-AS Member Extended Community">
            <![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type       |   Sub-Type    |    Global Administrator       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Global Administrator (cont.)  |               0               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type: TBD - non-transitive
Sub-Type: TBD
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </artset>      
        <t>
          The SAV rules are associated with a given neighbor AS of the service
          provider.
        </t>
        <t>
          The 4-octet Global Administrator field is set to the neighbor AS that
          the SAV table is attached to.  The Local Administrator field MUST be
          set to zero.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>SAV-D Origin-AS Member Extended Community</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="SAV-D Origin-AS Member Extended Community">
            <![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type       |   Sub-Type    |    Global Administrator       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Global Administrator (cont.)  |               0               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

Type: TBD - non-transitive
Sub-Type: TBD
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </artset>      
        <t>
          The SAV rules are associated with a given originating AS.  This
          membership enables such use cases as including the AS numbers in a
          customer cone.
        </t>
        <t>
          BGP speakers implementing <xref target="RFC8210"/> and ensuring that
          all Origin AS state used for SAV rules is present in their RPKI ROA
          cache MAY obtain the prefixes for their SAV Rules from that mechanism
          rather than BGP.
        </t>
        <t>
          The 4-octet Global Administrator field is set to the neighbor AS that
          the SAV table is attached to.  The Local Administrator field MUST be
          set to zero.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>SAV-D Operational Model</name>

      <t>The method by which a set of SAV Rules is determined for a given
        interface remains a somewhat contentious discussion.  For purposes of
        this document, it is presumed that a "SAV Controller" exists to
        calculate the appropriate SAV rules for the deployment and that such a
        controller implements the extensions defined in this document to
        provision SAV within the network.
      </t>

      <t>
        Each forwarding element implementing SAV will be provisioned with the
        per-interface SAV-D memberships for the SAV Rules implemented by that
        device.  This state constitutes a logical SAV Table.
      </t>
       
      <section>
        <name>SAV-D Route Distribution and Scaling</name>

        <t>
          The SAV Controller originates BGP SAV-D Routes with appropriate membership
          Extended Communities to each forwarding element.  When the device has
          matching membership for such SAV-D routes in a SAV Table, it installs
          that route in that logical SAV Table using the standard BGP Decision
          Process to choose the best SAV Route when multiple candidate routes
          exist.
        </t>

        <t>
          <xref target="RFC4684"/> SHOULD be deployed between BGP speakers
          distributing SAV-D Routes.
        </t>

        <t>
          SAV-D BGP speakers SHOULD originate <xref target="RFC4684"/>
          routes for SAV-D Neighor-AS and Origin-AS Member Extended Communities.
          Such routes will attract SAV Rules that may be used in-common across
          multiple SAV Tables in a deployment.
        </t>

        <section>
          <name>Leveraging RPKI-RTR</name>

          <t>
            In deployments where it is known that the SAV Controller would be
            emitting SAV Routes with Origin-AS Member Extended Communities that
            are identical with the RPKI ROA state carried in RPKI-RTR 
            (<xref target="RFC8210"/>), implementations MAY exclude originating 
            <xref target="RFC4684"/> routes for these Origin-AS Member Extended
            Communities and instead derive the local SAV Rules for their SAV
            Tables from the received RPKI-RTR state.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section>
          <name>Node-specific Extended Community scaling considerations</name>
          <t>
            Some SAV Routes have membership that is only only node-specific, i.e.
            contains only node-specific SAV-D Extended Communities. Distribution
            of these routes to all iBGP speakers within an AS, either via
            full-mesh iBGP or route reflection, will result in SAV-D BGP speakers
            receiving SAV Routes they do not care about.
          </t>

          <t>
            SAV-D BGP speakers SHOULD originate <xref target="RFC4684"/> routes
            for the Node Target Extended Communities.  At the same time, such
            speakers SHOULD NOT originate <xref target="RFC4684"/> routes for
            SAV-D node-specific Extended Communities.  The Node Target Extended
            Community is sufficient to attract the appropriate SAV-D Routes
            without needing to expose internal membership details.
          </t>

          <t>
            As an optimization, implementations MAY distribute such
            node-specific SAV-D Routes using "targeted" BGP sessions.  In this
            case, a dedicated BGP session between a SAV Controller and a SAV-D
            speaker is used to distribute node-specific BGP routes.  Such routes
            SHOULD be marked with the <xref target="RFC1997"/> NO_ADVERTISE
            community to prevent further redistribution.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Completeness of SAV information and enabling enforcement</name>

        <t>
          Even presuming pervasive and instantaneous deployment of SAV in a
          network, many documents discuss the problems associated with
          incomplete SAV information.  Such issues can include incorrectly
          passing traffic that should have been blocked or blocking traffic that
          should have been passed.
        </t>

        <t>
          Forwarding resources utilized by an implementation to enforce SAV may
          take time to program.  Such programming MUST be in-place with full
          state and correct prior to enforcement.  Failure to do so may result
          in incorrect enforcement.  Implementations SHOULD NOT enable
          enforcement of SAV until the state is fully programmed.
        </t>

        <t>
          One possible mechanism for controlling the activation of enforcement
          is careful control of a SAV-D "default" route for the node.  In
          circumstances where SAV Rules are primarily of the form of an
          allow-list, enforcement of block activity can be modeled as a
          "default" block action.  As long as the default is signaled last and
          its processing is deferred until other installation of SAV Table state
          is complete, inappropriate dropping of traffic may be minimized.
        </t>

        <t>
          Note that BGP does not permit careful sequencing of NLRI distribution
          within the protocol.  Routes advertised "last" are only done so
          between a pair of BGP speakers on a session.  Implementations might
          otherwise re-order advertised NLRI while propagating BGP routes
          according to their own desires.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        A huge list to come.  In particular, incorrect or incomplete
        installation of SAV in a network while having attracted traffic to that
        network by normal BGP means is harmful to the Internet.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1213.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1997.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4684.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8210.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8955.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8956.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.huang-savnet-sav-table.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-node-target-ext-comm"/>

        
      </references>
 
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8704.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sidrops-bar-sav.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section>
      <name>Encoding choices, why not Flowspec version 2?</name>

      <t>
        SAV enforcement of SAV rules in many ways resembles an access control
        list (ACL), which are often implemented via firewalls.  BGP Flowspec 
        <xref target="RFC8955"/> is capable of distributing IP source address
        filtering to be instantiated in firewalls.  However, Flowspec's original
        design for mitigating distributed denial of service (DDoS) attacks
        generally has meant that rules distributed via Flowspec are intended to
        be applied to the interfaces of all Flowspec routers in a network.
      </t>
      <t>
        The <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-interfaceset"/> feature
        provides scoped application of Flowspec filters.  This feature inspires
        some of the applicability of the SAV-D Device-Specific Group Member
        Extended Community.
      </t>
      <t>
        Given the overlapping nature of SAV enforcement behavior, and firewalls
        that may be programmed via Flowspec, should SAV enforcement be encoded
        there?
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>SAV enforcement is not required to be implemented in a forwarding
          element's firewall infrastructure.  Encoding SAV state in firewall
          functionality implies that this might be the case.  (Namespace
          confusion.)
        </li>
        <li>Flowspec provides for ordered filter installation.  If a SAV rule is
          present in flowspec, and implemented in something other than the
          firewall infrastructure, and filtering is not executed in the expected
          order, that's a problem.  Minimally, it is a matter of violating the
          "Principle of Least Astonishment".  Moreover, firewall applications
          built on the expectation that rules are executed in a particular order
          may be fail to execute as expected due to the firewall term
          dependencies.
        </li>
        <li><xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flowspec-v2"/> proposes a
          user-managed term order mechanism in additition to the default term
          order that Flowspec generates based on filtering components.  This could
          be leveraged to order SAV rules in a more appropriately logical place in
          the filter relative to an implementations forwarding pipeline; e.g.
          "last".  However, this still presumes to know how a given platform that
          does not instantiate SAV filtering will perform enforcement.
        </li>
        <li>The placement of SAV-D in a different AFI/SAFI than Flowspec also
          permits for the distribution of SAV rules distinctly from a BGP
          routing topology that may carry Flowspec.  Similarly, a separate
          AFI/SAFI means that implementations do not conflate distribution of
          firewall state vs.  SAV state in terms of ordering and prioritization.
          SAV state will, in the majority of cases, significantly exceed the
          number of entries typically carried in Flowspec for firewall by
          several orders of magnitude.
        </li>
        <li>Flowspec does have a form of encoding that carries a Route
          Distinguisher for VPN Flowspec purposes in a VPN-specific AFI/SAFI.
          However, that format currently carries the expectation that it is
          accompanied by a BGP Route Target for installing the routes in a VRF
          context.
        </li>
        <li>Finally, a significant amount of the fragility that Flowspec is
          subject to is a result of the complexity needed to encode the various
          components in a term in the NLRI.  SAV-D state has the much simpler
          need to encode only a RD, and a IPv4/IPv6 prefix.  This also has the
          benefit of being not only "fit for purpose", but can pack better in
          BGP Updates since Flowspec v1/v2 NLRI have more overhead.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        It is a valid observation that the Group Member Extended Communities
        defined for SAV-D may have overlapping usefulness for general-purpose
        BGP Flowspec applications.  Future versions of this document may
        repurpose the Extended Communities for such general use.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <!-- an Acknowledgements section is optional -->
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Discussions with Nan Geng and Susan Hares at IETF-119 were helpful in
        formulating the requirements for this draft.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <!-- a Contributors section is optional -->
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
